so the simple barrier operation doesn't
work entirely and we look now at why it
doesn't work let's consider only two
cores core zero which we will show in
blue color what it's doing and core one
which will show in this color what it's
doing what they're both doing initially
is doing something before they arrive to
the barrier and let's say that core zero
arrives here first so what core zero
does is resets release to 0 increments
the count to 1
unlocks the lock
checks whether the count is equal to 2
and starts spinning waiting for the
release to become 1. so now release is
still 0 because
we just reset it and core zero is gonna
stay here spinning so what core zero
does is it essentially
does a load word of release c0 and will
check again and it keeps doing that
now let's see what happens when core 1
arrives
normally what should happen is core 1
arrives doesn't do this because count is
now 1
increments the count exits the critical
section sees that the count is equal to
two
resets the count
sets the release to one
and now
core one proceeds past the barrier what
should happen now is course zero should
see this release that we just set to 1
and also proceed past the barrier so
what should happen is
really that we set the release to 1 here
and core 0
sees that
exits the barrier and from then
everything will actually be correct but
let's say that core zero has been
checking the release
however when the store happens core zero
is delayed for example it's executing
some sort of an interrupt function so
for a while it's suspended in this place
in the code and cannot read the release
fast enough in that case we don't have
this
and core 0 is still stuck here in a
correct barrier implementation core 0
will eventually leave at some point it
will return from the interrupt read the
release that is 1 and proceed
however
what happens if core 0 is waiting here
while core 1 after releasing and exiting
the barrier
does very little work
and then comes back to the barrier again
it sees that the count is zero
because it reset it to zero when it was
releasing the barrier and sets the
release to one and now it writes zero to
the release variable and now even if
core zero checks the release here and
sees what it is it's gonna see this zero
so core zero is gonna proceed to wait
here for a very long time meanwhile core
one
increments the count to one checks if
it's equal to two for this second
iteration of the barrier it's not two
so court one
is now gonna spin waiting for somebody
to release the second instance of the
barrier while core zero is gonna be
waiting there
in the first instance of the barrier and
never being released so the only thing
that can release core one now is if core
zero somehow left
and enter the second instance of the
barrier the only thing that can release
core zero however is if somebody
comes and releases here but that's not
gonna be core tool so now we have a
deadlock situation